Vincent van Gogh,
a painter who breaks the boundaries of
art.
Today, his paintings are among the
[music] most famous and most expensive
in the world.
>> For you, sir, 75 million.
>> This image of the tragic genius between
genius and madness.
>> A painter who lives with prostitutes.
>> That is a lie.
>> Who is considered a troublemaker by his
colleagues.
Who mutilates himself [music] out of
despair.
>> A very difficult person to place.
>> Vincent van Gogh dies poor and
misunderstood.
Who was he really? A madman or a genius
with a very vulnerable soul?
Researchers are using state-of-the-art
methods to find the real Vincent van
Gogh behind this mysterious [music]
figure.
>> He has very high ambitions, very high
hopes, big dreams.
>> They want to unlock the secrets of his
art
and to shed new light on the low points
of his life.
>> It's phenomenal to think that he managed
to accomplish this within a space of 10
years, to become [music] a leading
member of the avant-garde, starting from
somebody that could hardly draw.
>> The results of science paint a new,
startlingly different picture of this
giant of art.
Here in a mental asylum, Vincent van
Gogh produces some of his greatest
masterpieces.
The former monastery of Saint Paul de
Mausole near Saint-Rémy in Provence.
In May 1889,
the Dutchman seeks refuge behind its
thick walls from the life that
overwhelms him.
Refuge from the people who don't
understand him.
And he hopes for help in the face of the
mysterious seizures that haunt him.
What keeps Van Gogh alive is his art.
He wants to, he has to, keep painting.
The Starry Night. No one before him had
ever painted a night sky [music] in this
way.
Instead of depicting reality true to
nature,
Van Gogh alienates and abstracts, thus
anticipating modernist painting.
In the mental asylum in Saint-Rémy,
Vincent van Gogh struggles with the
greatest crisis of his life.
After a strange quarrel, he mutilates
his left ear.
Flurries of mental derangement keep him
from painting again and again.
He eats paint and drinks turpentine.
>> Van Gogh says that he has that he
[music] has hallucinations, that he
hears
things
that he really [music] didn't at during
those attacks, that he doesn't know what
he's doing.
>> Van Gogh suspects that his feverish
creative work is partly to blame for the
seizures.
He accepts them as the price to pay for
great art.
He wrote to his brother Theo,
"My pictures cost me dearly.
Sometimes, perhaps even in blood [music]
and brains."
In fact, Van Gogh wears himself out
painting.
362 paintings in the last 2 years of his
life alone.
And he revolutionized art.
>> You have to understand that what Van
Gogh was making at the time was quite
out of line of everything.
The interesting [music] that he added to
art and art history is the fact that you
can think of the world as [music]
something in lines.
That you see movement in his pictures
and that's something totally new.
>> But above all, Van Gogh depicts the
world in completely new, luminous
colors.
>> He was constantly pushing the
boundaries, so there's a kind of level
of intensity to his color in many of his
[music] paintings that was
really novel in his time.
Since then we have Andy Warhol and
Gerhard Richter and other
colorists who, you know, played at the
very edges of what color can be, but we
have to think back what this looked like
in the 1880s. It was very shocking.
>> In his day, the verdict was that such
art cannot be the product of a healthy
mind.
But this assessment is overturned in the
following decades.
>> Somehow he becomes Vincent van Gogh, the
creator of this huge body of
masterpieces that have won over the the
the hearts and minds of the world.
>> What was his driving force?
Are his paintings the spontaneous result
of his madness?
Or the expression of a highly sensitive
artist's soul?
Anyone who wants to understand Van Gogh
and his gigantic [music]
oeuvre will probably come closest to him
in Amsterdam.
As the world's largest collection of
[music] the artist's work, the Van Gogh
Museum attracts millions of visitors
year after year. But his works are also
meticulously studied here.
In order to preserve them for posterity
in the best [music] possible way,
researchers want to understand exactly
how Van Gogh's masterpieces were created
and how they were originally intended to
appear.
>> It really started when we started to
examine each painting one by one,
taking out of its frame. Often
underneath the frames, [music] where the
paint has been protected from light,
there were uh remnants of much brighter
color around the edges.
>> The intense colors make Van Gogh's
Sunflowers the eye-catcher of every
exhibition. [music]
What might the magically luminous still
life have looked like fresh on the
easel?
That's what a unique experiment by the
museum aims to show.
The search for the secrets of Van Gogh's
colors begins in the laboratory of the
Imperial Cultural Heritage Office of the
Netherlands with tiny samples of the
painting.
Under the microscope, the cross-sections
make layers of color that have already
faded on the surface visible again.
Van Gogh's very volatile red, [music]
for example,
a mass spectrometer reveals the chemical
elements [music] contained in each
sample.
These, in turn, reveal the composition
of the colors and reveal the extent of
the discoloration.
But the researchers do not leave it at
that.
They want to combine science and art.
Their new knowledge makes it possible to
reproduce Van Gogh's original colors
using old recipes from the [music]
archive.
The aim of the project to have the
famous masterpiece copied as accurately
as possible.
The museum entrusts Charlotte O.
Caspers, artist and restorer, with the
task.
>> So, there's a really strange thing about
the sunflowers actually. Everybody in
the world knows them, but the painting
already has aged, so it's it's like an
old person you [music] get to know
whereas has been just newly born when it
came from Van Gogh's easel and then it
was really bright. It's famous,
everybody knows it, but not in the way
he made it.
>> Charlotte Caspers has to understand the
structure of the painting in detail
before she can reconstruct. [music]
To do this, she uses x-ray images, color
cross sections, so-called XRF scans, and
transmitted light photos of the
painting. [music]
>> So all these things combined
um
yeah, [music] give quite a good plan of
of how to start and and what to use, how
to work.
I love doing this and I always do this
with a lot of respect because it also
feels very
private [music] when you go so deep in
somebody else's
work. You see what he was looking for,
searching for,
uh why he made changes, um
yes, it feels very intimate.
>> For Charlotte Caspers,
>> [music]
>> repainting the sunflowers means
channeling Van Gogh,
feeling how he was, who he was.
Vincent was born and raised in Groot
Zundert, a village in the south of
Holland.
His father, Theodorus, is a strict
Protestant priest.
Mother Anna, bourgeois and status
conscious, keeps her children away from
the poor peasant children.
But the siblings have each other.
Vincent is especially close with his
little brother Theo.
He invents [music] games for him
and they explore nature together.
>> Vincent, see here I found an egg.
>> Great, take it to mama.
>> Theo is Vincent's closest confidant
throughout his life. Perhaps the only
person who ever really understood him.
>> He seems to have been to certain extent
indeed an [music] an a lonely boy, too.
I didn't think an out an outsider.
>> And an oddball.
Tirelessly and meticulously he collects,
examines, and catalogs beetles, plants,
and birds' nests.
He lives in his own world. He devotes
himself to things that excite him with
an almost fanatical devotion and
passion.
>> Vincent, dinner is ready.
>> Can I just finish doing something?
>> You must come down now at once.
>> No.
>> Little Vincent often argues with his
parents and withdraws from them.
>> His father and his mother believe that
it was crucial for their children to
temper their speech, to temper their
emotions, and to live life in an orderly
way.
And all of a sudden they have this child
who right from the beginning didn't
conform to anything. In fact, the maids
called him um the strange boy.
>> His whole life,
>> [music]
>> Vincent's parents do not accept that he
is different. And deny him the
recognition he so longs for.
>> [music]
>> At a loss as to what to make of their
strange boy, they arrange for him to
train in his uncle's art printing
empire.
Vincent is 17 years old at the time.
For the first time, he finds himself in
the world of art
as a salesman.
This only existing photo of [music] him
is taken 2 years later when Vincent is
transferred because of his rude manner.
>> And he was shipped off to to a a clerk
at the [music] at the enterprise in
London.
He was fired from that. He goes to Paris
>> [music]
>> and he insulted the clients. If somebody
was looking at a painting that he didn't
like, he would go up to them and say,
"Only somebody with terrible taste would
be interested in that."
in the enterprise he was working in. So,
they not only fired him, they banished
him from ever stepping foot in the
gallery again.
>> He was a bookseller. He uh
he uh and then he went back to London
and uh to to England again and there he
uh
uh worked as [music] a teacher in a
school for a very poor salary.
>> At that point,
um
he basically tried to become a
missionary.
>> The Borinage coalfield in Belgium.
After his constant [music] failure,
Vincent finds work as a lay preacher
here at the age of 25.
>> Jesus Christ was a carpenter's son. He
worked for 30 years in a humble
workshop.
He was a laborer with marks of a of a
weariness and of suffering on his face.
Just just like you who simple and proud
and
believing in God enter the mine day
after day.
Talk of revolution, but God wants us to
live humbly on this earth of his, this
blessed earth.
>> Van Gogh wants his congregation to live
as simply and piously as he does.
His sermons are not only muddled,
however, they also strike the wrong
note.
The downtrodden miners are not comforted
by Van Gogh's words.
They see the young man rather as a
religious fanatic who overdoes it with
his priestly existence.
He lets himself go to such an extent
that even the dusty coal miners consider
him a filthy disgrace.
Once again, Van Gogh fails here, too.
Despite his deeply and sincerely felt
religious vocation.
>> It says It says here.
It's really very easy. It's It's in
here. It's It's all in here.
>> His community turns away from him.
They even ensure that he is recalled.
For Vincent, it is the lowest point of
his life so far.
He is penniless, unemployed, aimless.
His decline also disturbs his family.
His own father wants to have him
committed to a mental institution.
>> It gives you a sense of what the family
felt about him, that they thought he
needed to be committed. I don't think it
is
takes um Sigmund Freud to understand
that for many of us uh uh
trying to to live up to our parents'
expectations, especially when they we we
haven't in uh done that, is a very
strong motive for us, and it certainly
was for Vincent.
>> He is extremely disappointed to have
failed again.
To be abandoned by everyone again.
Deeply despondent, Vincent writes to his
brother Theo.
>> [music]
>> He was searching [music] for a
a place in the world for himself.
I think he was longing to consult
people, but also to be consoled.
>> Together with other art historians,
Nienke Bakker has analyzed the extensive
correspondence between Vincent and Theo.
The letters provide a unique glimpse
into Vincent's thoughts, plans, and
inspirations, and also his spiritual
life.
Thanks to the letters, we also [music]
learn of Theo's reaction to his
brother's despair.
He responds with a proposal that gives
Vincent a new lease of life.
Theo knows his older brother likes to
draw.
If Vincent would like to try his hand as
an artist, he would support him
financially.
Still in Borinage, Vincent sets to work.
At the age of 27, an age when other
artists are creating masterpieces, Van
Gogh is still painting rudimentary
figures [music] in pencil.
Van Gogh is not gifted with natural
talent.
But, just as his tendency to excess was
disastrous in bourgeois life, with art,
his fanatical zeal will prove to be a
stroke of luck.
He works tirelessly.
Can you move a little?
Yes.
>> [music]
>> In The Hague, he finds a deaf-mute
pensioner who lets him dress him up for
a pittance.
At the time, Van Gogh struggled with
dimensions and perspective.
He therefore made use of a perspective
frame as an aid.
In his [music] letters to Theo, he
enthusiastically describes its
construction and function.
In fact, [music] the self-taught artist
will be dependent on this crutch for a
long time.
>> [music]
>> This is apparent in works created years
later,
like this one from Montmartre in Paris.
The auxiliary lines are visible here
even to the naked eye.
>> [music]
>> Van Gogh, who stubbornly refuses a
classical artist's training, needs the
aid to convey dimensions correctly on
the canvas.
At the time, Van Gogh was living with
Sien Hoornik, a prostitute with
illegitimate children,
much to the displeasure of his family.
>> Vincent knew that his parents and also
Theo were against his relationship, but
he also felt very attached to her and to
her children. This is the only time that
he actually had his own his own family.
>> Vincent gives in to pressure from his
family and ends his relationship [music]
with Sien.
Despite his nonconformist nature, he
longs for companionship.
Yet once again, he is alone.
Five years into his career as an artist,
at the age of 32, Van Gogh believes he
has finally created his first great
masterpiece,
The Potato Eaters.
For months he painted portraits and made
individual studies for this [music]
picture.
As an artist, he hopes for the
recognition that is denied him as a
human being.
The reactions to the earth-colored work,
however, are painful.
His brother Theo and fellow painters
>> [music]
>> considered it old-fashioned and
unsellable.
He finally enrolls at the Art Academy in
Antwerp that wants to put him in the
beginners course.
>> [music]
>> Van Gogh is in danger of failing on this
classic path of a painter even at the
basic skills that are required.
So, how does this amateur become one of
the greatest artists in history?
Christie's auction house in New York in
1990,
>> [music]
>> seemingly out of nowhere, a painting
appears on the auctioneer's stage that
has not been seen in public for decades.
>> 35 million, 36 million, 27 million, 28
million, 29 million.
>> The famous portrait of Dr. Gachet.
Painted in 1890,
it is the last major portrait the
Dutchman painted before his death.
It shows Van Gogh's neurologist, Paul
Ferdinand Gachet.
When Van Gogh made it,
he was so poor that he had to keep
exchanging drawings and paintings for
food and paint.
>> [music]
>> Selling in the room now. All done, then.
Against the telephone. Not yours here.
Fair warning.
At 75 million dollars.
For you, sir. 75 million.
>> 75 million dollars.
This makes the painting the most
expensive work of art of its time.
The buyer,
a Japanese businessman.
The story of Dr. Gachet, however, is not
only one of top [music] prices, but also
an art thriller.
The Städel Museum in Frankfurt [music]
is involved.
In 2019, it celebrates Van Gogh as the
inspiration for the German
Expressionists with an exhibition
and explains why Van Gogh became so
popular in Germany at the beginning of
the 20th century. The fact that Dr.
Gachet of all people is missing from
this exhibition
is all the more regrettable for the
museum as it had acquired the famous
[music] portrait in 1911.
The only remnant of the famous portrait
is stored in the museum's painting depot
in the basement.
It is the original frame for Dr. Gachet
kept as a reminder of scandalous [music]
events.
>> That was really one of the key works
here in the collection. He was initially
presented in his pioneering role, in his
role as an inspirational figure of the
German avant-garde.
And I also think that was part of the
downfall because of course these were
the artworks that were taken down here
in the museum in 1933.
>> Provenance researcher Iris Schmeisser
had delved deeply into the Dr. Gachet
case file for the Städel Museum.
The National Socialists' justification
for the confiscation
problematic foreigner.
>> And with regard to the so-called
problematic foreigners, that's a quote,
that's really the term that was used
which also included Van Gogh.
There was talk of mental perversion,
aberration, degeneration, being out of
sorts.
>> Dr. Gachet ends up in Berlin along with
paintings by other denigrated [music]
artists.
>> They were first stored there in a
granary.
And then Hitler and Goebbels inspected
these stocks.
And in this context, we can assume that
they plan to exploit these products of
decaying art, in inverted commas,
to make money.
And Dr. Gachet then became something
like a pilot project to try this out.
>> Reichsmarschall Hermann Göring sells the
painting to a dealer in Amsterdam.
Here its trace [music] is lost. Until it
reappears at the auction in New York 50
years later.
Only to disappear from the public eye
once again.
But how did The Potato Eaters painter
become the famous Dr. Gachet painter?
How did Van Gogh progress from the dusty
earth colors to the garish contrasts?
The transformation takes place in Paris
in 1886.
Where Vincent [music] van Gogh finds the
style that makes him immortal as an
artist.
>> [music]
>> Vincent soaks up everything Europe's art
capital has to offer.
Like here [music] in the Louvre.
>> He had something like a photographic
memory. So when he would sit and study a
painting which he could sometimes do for
as long as a day, he would remember the
passages of color,
brushwork that that created a kind of
imaginary museum.
>> This insatiable thirst for art is only
one reason for his visit to Paris.
Here Vincent is [music] also reunited
with his brother Theo. Who lives in
Paris as a successful art dealer.
>> You're always welcome in Paris.
>> [laughter]
[music]
>> Come, let's go home.
>> Theo's monthly cash injections are
hardly enough for Vincent's artistic
ambitions.
He is simply looking for a cheap place
to live.
And therefore wants to move [music] in
with Theo.
Construction of the Eiffel Tower is just
beginning in Paris.
Industrialization changes the city.
And science changes the way we look at
the world.
Photography makes it possible to capture
their image.
Classical painting faces serious
competition.
It is an overwrought fatalistic time.
L'envie de l'abou,
the desire for booze and excess, reigns
in the city's cabarets and cafes.
Poets drinking themselves to death and
painters losing their minds
exert great fascination at the end of
the century.
Vincent lives with his younger brother
in Paris for 2 years.
>> Theo, I'm back.
Good.
>> The art dealer brings Vincent into
contact with the Parisian avant-garde.
Painters whose works finally banished
the old-fashioned from Van Gogh's works.
>> Vincent, can you come here, please?
I was able to buy one of
Toulouse-Lautrec's paintings.
>> Poudre de riz is the name of the
portrait of the young woman at the
table.
Vincent is thrilled and at the same time
inspired to evolve the avant-garde style
even further.
>> See here how the color draws the eye?
Now, imagine the tablecloth blue
and the tin orange.
How intensely that would shine.
>> Toulouse-Lautrec, Georges Seurat,
Louis Anquetin,
or Émile Bernard,
Vincent's new acquaintances have long
been experimenting with shapes and
colors, dots and surfaces.
Van Gogh wants to be like them,
but here too, he remains an outsider.
>> He goes to the soirées [music]
of Toulouse-Lautrec and Suzanne Valadon
tells afterwards what this consisted of.
Simply a boy and a person who came in
with a canvas underneath his arm, would
sit in the corner, would say nothing,
and at the end of the the soirée he left
again.
>> But Vincent also pushes ahead
enthusiastically with his painting on
his own.
In no time at all, he masters the
stylistic devices of the avant-garde.
He feverishly experiments with the
element that would retain the greatest
significance for him until the end of
his life,
color.
>> [music]
>> With the help of woolen threads, he
tests contrasts with which he wants to
increase the intensity of his pictures.
>> [music]
>> It is the awakening of an exceptional
artist.
>> It's not that he abandons what he's done
in the Netherlands. He's um
transforming it, but he's
keeping to the [music] the very
pronounced brushstrokes and
his very personal style.
>> His artistic transformation is made
clear by two self-portraits that Van
Gogh painted in Paris. The first was
painted shortly after his arrival and is
still in the old earth colors.
The second [music] he paints shortly
before his departure, a self-confident
artist in Van Gogh's famous cobalt blue.
However, his face also shows signs of
exhaustion.
>> In Paris he got lost. It has something
[music] to do with the stress, indeed to
to be part of the avant-garde at the
time [music]
and for that reason he went to the south
of France and had a kind of idea that
that was paradise, which of course it
wasn't, but that's what he expected of
it.
>> Vincent van Gogh arrives in Provence in
the spring of 1888.
It is the beginning of the two most
important years of his creative life.
>> [music]
>> In the meantime, he is thrown off the
shackles of realistic portrayals.
Here, he finally wants to paint things
as he sees them and feels them.
He wants to capture the truth, the
essence of things.
And in doing so, he breaks the
boundaries of art at the time.
Without regard for his health, he
[music] paints everything he sees in
front of his canvas on a piecework
basis.
180 paintings in just over [music] a
year, an enormous legacy and a
captivating style.
>> [music]
>> The sheer physicality of these paintings
and and [music] the very bright, vivid
color schemes and most of all the
emotions that this conveys, you really
sense the
>> [music]
>> It's the feeling that he wants to
convey.
>> The city of Arles and its surroundings
are now both the setting and the motif
for his work. This is where he takes up
residence.
Are his aspirations now fulfilled in
Arles?
>> I think he remained the outsider. He He
was not part of the community in that
sense. I mean, he was looked upon by the
people in the town, who's this strange
artist uh wandering around.
>> Van Gogh's Cafe Terrace in the evening
is one of the paintings created in
Arles,
so famous today that the cafe is one of
the main attractions for tourists
visiting Provence.
>> Just a few hundred meters further on on
Place Lamartine is the no less famous
yellow house.
Van Gogh rented it in the late summer of
and captured his new home on canvas in
glaring contrasts.
On the first floor, he furnishes his
bedroom.
He paints it in colors that are meant to
convey peace and security to the viewer.
Not in the picture
12 chairs that he buys as soon as he
moves in
for all the artist colleagues who are to
work and live with him in Arles.
>> His bedroom is the one on the left and
the one on the right [music] is going to
be Gauguin's bedroom when he comes to
stay because Vincent had a plan. [music]
Wouldn't it be great? I'm living in this
house. I love this little town. You can
get around. There's a million subjects
that we can paint. Why [music] don't I
create a studio of the south?
>> An artist [music] commune.
Van Gogh paints sunflowers in all
variations to express his joy at the
guests he hopes will soon arrive.
He finds it easier to communicate his
feelings with color than with words.
Probably the most famous of the
sunflower paintings can be admired today
in the Van Gogh Museum in Amsterdam.
But what did Vincent's welcome picture
look like when he painted it and the
colors had not yet faded?
After Charlotte Caspers [music] has
completed her analysis
she can finally begin to repaint the
masterpiece with a scientifically
reproduced original [music] colors.
She knows from the artist's
correspondence that he planned his
paintings meticulously
contrary to the myth of the impulsive
mad genius.
His works were well thought out in the
best sense.
>> [music]
>> But he was incapable of painting slowly.
>> With Van Gogh in general, he works often
spontaneous, but you can compare it with
sporting. When you run every day, you're
very very good in it. And it's also with
the the rhythm of his brush strokes and
in the the thickness of his paint. And
that's because he's doing it every day.
That's his spontaneity, but also this
organization in it.
It's really difficult [music] to uh
to mimic. And it's very unnatural to
copy very secure with all this research
[music] uh data
uh a painting that was
um painted really quickly. So, that's
that's always the
the tension.
I should paint it [music] quick as well,
but then it would not be a
reconstruction of his painting. Then it
would be my painting.
When somebody
stands behind me and looks at the
painting, uh I feel very vulnerable. I
feel like um
they think that I'm exaggerating.
Whereas I I'm using the same pigments.
>> To see the world through Van Gogh's
eyes.
Thanks to Charlotte Caspers
reconstruction, we can experience this
impression 130 years later.
>> [music]
>> This is what the sunflowers look like
today.
>> [music]
>> And this is how they might have looked
when the painting was still wet on Van
Gogh's easel
before the red faded and the yellow
discolored.
>> For me, it was an important moment,
yeah.
>> [music]
>> Suddenly, I thought, "Okay,
this is this is for half a religion."
Because the color that you see there is
indeed so fresh, so so colorful that you
indeed get
uh uh
uh
you you you you you you you you you you
you glad.
>> "I feel what I paint. I paint what I
feel." Van Gogh once wrote.
When he painted the sunflowers in Arles,
>> [music]
>> he must have been very happy
and full of anticipation.
The painter Paul Gauguin confirms his
arrival. Finally, a brother in spirit
[music]
with whom he hopes to share life and
art.
But in expectation of his guest, [music]
Vincent works even harder and faster.
In anticipation, he tires and burns
himself out recklessly.
>> When you look at how he worked, how
immensely productive he was, he was
almost working day and night uh on
paintings. Uh he was not eating well.
[music] He was drinking too much. I
mean, he did do
a lot of harm to his his health.
Before Gauguin came, he actually wrote
that he was so tired that he had to
sleep for 2 days and
>> [music]
>> uh take some rest um which he didn't
want to because he wanted to do all
these paintings.
>> For the eagerly awaited guest, [music]
the famous sunflowers.
They were actually created as wall
decoration for [music] Paul Gauguin's
room.
What happens next is still the subject
of much speculation [music]
today.
The author Bernadette Murphy has
painstakingly reconstructed what exactly
happened [music] in the Yellow House in
the autumn of 1888 on the basis of
countless documents in the Arles town
archives.
>> Merci beaucoup.
>> Vincent's idea of an artist's commune
was to come to a dramatic [music]
end shortly after Gauguin's arrival in
art.
>> An undernourished and overexcited, yet
highly ambitious Van Gogh,
and the self-confident Gauguin.
Two exceptional artists, but also two
excessive characters in a confined
space.
That could not go well for long.
>> Finally, things start to go a little bit
strange towards the end of the month,
November. The weather is changing, they
can't go out and paint quite so much.
They just they start arguing about
pretty much everything.
>> [music]
>> Do I really seem like that to you?
>> Like a monkey with a paintbrush?
>> At the beginning when Gauguin came, he
was I tend to think a little bit more
friendly to Gauguin in the terms of
well,
eager to learn something from Gauguin.
But at the end of the stay of Gauguin,
he certainly tried to do and to show
Gauguin what he was capable of doing.
>> The true artist
creates paintings from his imagination,
from his memory.
>> Have you still not understood it? I want
to see the truth of things and then I
want to capture it on canvas.
>> The quarrels continue [music] to
escalate until the day before Christmas
Eve.
>> Just because you can paint from memory,
doesn't mean all the other artists in
the world have to do without.
>> recognize what is true when I see it in
front of me. I can't just make it up and
then
That is a lie. You're lying to the
viewer, man.
>> And the reality of your sunflowers is a
color that makes you go blind.
>> After this dispute, Gauguin probably
wanted to turn his back on Van Gogh for
good.
>> Van Gogh was just
ruined by this because he had worked so
hard to create a little community of
artists. He had finally gotten Gauguin
to come down and live with him and deep
down I think he understood that he would
never be able to live with anybody.
>> And since really showing more and more
signs of disturbance, I'm going to
[music] tell you what I've concluded to
try and understand what happened.
Sometime after dinner, Gauguin goes into
the park.
>> In his memoirs written many years later,
Gauguin claims that Van Gogh threatened
him with a gun in Arles.
>> [music]
>> A cut-throat razor
and he was sufficiently scared
and Vincent [music] returns to the
Yellow House.
>> [music]
>> Gauguin does not follow him.
Instead, he spends the night in a hotel.
Meanwhile, the drama unfolds in the
Yellow House.
That night, with the very razor he had
previously wielded to threaten Gauguin,
Van Gogh inflicts a serious injury to
his own ear.
>> He made a summary bandage out of rags
and then walked for 5 minutes
to the House of Tolerance number one.
>> The street where the brothel was located
still looks the same today.
>> So, here we are now in Rue du Boule
d'Or.
Unfortunately, the House of Tolerance
number [music] one no longer exists.
It was on the corner here, just behind
my back. You'll um
you can see that there's cars parked
here now, but the walls are still there.
Vincent Van Gogh came here, walked up
the street. He must [music] have seen a
light on the corner. It was the most
prominent of all the brothels.
>> [music]
>> What happens next was reported to a
gendarme shortly afterwards by
eyewitnesses at the brothel.
Later, the mysterious events even end up
in the local newspaper. [music]
>> Can you fetch Rachel, please?
>> Rachel.
>> Take good care of it, please.
>> [crying]
>> Give it to me.
>> Until his death, [music]
Van Gogh remained silent about what
moved him to harm himself so severely.
But he did process this event in his
paintings.
In the dormitory of the asylum in Arles,
for example,
>> [music]
>> the asylum where Vincent was taken the
next day after policeman found him
unconscious at home.
>> [music]
>> And in self-portrait with a bandage.
But what actually happened?
What exactly did Van Gogh do to himself
that night?
In the course of her research,
Bernadette Murphy also comes across a
document in the archives of the
University of Berkeley that could solve
[music] this more than 130-year-old
mystery.
It was made by one of the few people who
saw Van Gogh's injury,
his doctor [music] in Arles.
>> It was a dream document to find. It's
[music] just a ripped-off piece of paper
from a doctor's prescription form, and
it's dated 1930.
>> [music]
>> 18th of August, 1930.
It says, "The ear was cut with a razor."
>> And the doctor even [music] describes
how Van Gogh must have proceeded.
>> Vincent pulled up his ear,
took a razor,
and sliced through his ear.
And then it says what the ear looked
like
afterwards.
And then he gives a little thing. He
says, "I'm very happy to give [music]
you this uh testimony
about my unhappy friend." [music] And he
signs it Dr. Rey.
>> A few months after this fit, Vincent
moves at his own request from Arles to
the mental asylum in Saint-Rémy, 30 km
away.
>> [music]
>> His mental and spiritual state unsettles
him.
Taking care of himself costs [music] him
too much energy.
Above all, Vincent wants to justify
Theo's trust and finally find success.
And to do that, he has to keep painting
against all odds.
He is now 36 years old.
In his 9 years as an artist, he has not
managed to stand on his own two feet
financially.
>> Yeah?
>> Your brother has sent a parcel.
>> Ah, finally.
Sent him a list 3 weeks ago with all the
colors that I
urgently need.
My brushes have all lost their hair.
Thank you.
>> Theo, now married, still sends him
paints, brushes, and canvases regularly.
These utensils are more important than
medicine for the restless artist,
[music]
artist's lifeline during this agonizing
period.
When he is afflicted by fits, he is
unable to paint.
But in the phases in between, Van Gogh
continues to create masterpieces such as
the famous Starry Night.
In this fantasy landscape, he mixes the
world outside his window with memories
and feelings in a grandiose pictorial
symbiosis.
>> [music]
>> The swirls of clouds and stars in
particular stand out with their
undulating lines. Some art historians
see in them the expression of inner
ecstatic [music] states, which,
according to Van Gogh in his letters,
the sight [music] of nature always
triggered in him. At the same time,
however, the stars also seem to have
been a source of comfort and hope for
him.
>> At one point, he actually says in his
letters, "When I have a feel for
something
for for religion,
I go out and paint the stars."
>> In the center of the picture, Van Gogh
has even hidden a wistful memory of his
childhood. Church steeples like this are
not to be found in Provence,
but they are in his Dutch homeland.
Today, it is difficult to know for sure
what demons tormented the patient
[music] Vincent van Gogh.
At the time, the director of the
institution in Saint-Rémy
believed it to be epilepsy with
delusional ideas.
It was to remain unchallenged as the
sole diagnosis.
Knowledge about mental illness was
limited at the time,
and the only therapy, regular baths,
does not help Vincent either.
After a year, he finally gives up his
confinement experiment and turns his
back on the south of France.
>> He realizes, of course, that he has to
go to society to become better.
>> [music]
>> He needs people around him.
I mean, he's living amidst patients.
Come on.
That doesn't help you.
>> In the summer resort town of
Auvers-sur-Oise, north of Paris, Vincent
van Gogh tries one last time to stand on
his own two feet.
Here, in the Auberge Ravoux, he lives
cheaply and all alone.
Several times he tries to lure Theo and
his wife Johanna to visit,
but this last attempt to find a family
also fails.
Instead, a terrible quarrel [music]
breaks out in Paris between the
brothers, who were always very close.
During this time, Vincent is under the
medical care of Dr. Gachet, the man
whose portrait will later fetch a record
price.
But Dr. Gachet will no longer be able to
help Vincent.
A few days after the confrontation with
Theo, on the 27th of July, 1890,
Vincent van Gogh goes to the fields
behind the church of Auvers.
There, he tries to take his own life
with a revolver.
Badly injured, the painter drags himself
[music] back to the Auberge.
The doctor who is summoned cannot save
Vincent van Gogh.
Theo has rushed from Paris
>> [music]
>> and sits in the chair next to him.
Vincent dies 2 days later, aged only 37.
>> It's clear that he was not uh hopeful
for the future, that he had a lot of
worries, that he was depressed. Um
the fact that he didn't want to be a
burden for Theo anymore [music]
was probably part of it, but um but
there's no there's not one reason, I
think, uh
why he decided to
to end his life.
>> The painter is buried in the Auvers
cemetery.
His brother Theo only lives half a year
longer.
He dies of syphilis.
The artist and his brother patron
rest side by side to this day.
Vincent van Gogh painted 90 paintings in
the 70 days he spent in Auvers.
One of the last,
a kind of legacy,
Wheat Field with Crows.
Vincent wrote to his brother that he
wanted to express sadness and extreme
[music] loneliness with this painting,
but also the vitality, the force of
nature,
>> [music]
>> which fascinated him throughout his
life.
The myth of the mad painter claims Van
Gogh painted like this because he was
crazy.
His letters and his art painted a
different picture.
Van Gogh painted in [music] this way
because his soul was so fragile.
His sensibility so vulnerable.
And his art was perhaps his only [music]
gateway to life.
Even painting could not [music] save
Vincent van Gogh in the end, but it made
him immortal. His life has moved and
influenced millions of people. His
example has freed artists [music] all
over the world from the constraints of
realism. And encouraged them to
experiment freely with colors and form.
>> He became an example for every artist.
If you want to achieve something and you
have a goal, please try it. Do it.
And
knowing that certain risks were
involved.
Because you could fail. Because you
could not sell. Because you could could
be poor, but if you believed in it, hey,
>> [music]
>> try it.
>> There's a sense in his many letters in
which he says, "Nothing could make me
happier than that the average person
would hang my paintings on their walls."
>> His wish actually came true.
With his paintings, he succeeded in
connecting with the souls of people all
over the world. This gave Vincent van
Gogh the companionship that was denied
him throughout his life.
>> Yeah.
Yeah.